<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tam quam, or, A attaint brought in the supream court of the King of kings, upon the statutes, Exod. 20. 7, 16 and Levit. 19. 12 against those modern jurors, who have found any indictments upon the statutes of 23 Eliz., 29 Eliz., or 3 Jacobi, against Protestants, for monthly absence from church, without any confession of the parties, or oath of witness against them, or made any presentments of them : contrary to the express letter of their oaths taken in a Court of Judgment, the course of the law of England, or any right reason : wherein is discoursed, whether any Protetant be concerned in that part of those laws? : the contrary is proved : as also whether a grand-jury's finding and indictment, be any evidence to a petit-jury? : the absurdness, and most pernicious consequents of which are detected, and the vengeance of God agaisnt false-swearing is declared / by one who prosecutes, as well for his sovereign lord the King of kings, as for the lives, liberties, and properties of all the subjects of England.</title>
            <author>One who persecutes as well for his sovereign lord the King of kings as for the lives, liberties, and properties of all the subjects of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11940649</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11940649</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51262</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51262)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 516:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tam quam, or, A attaint brought in the supream court of the King of kings, upon the statutes, Exod. 20. 7, 16 and Levit. 19. 12 against those modern jurors, who have found any indictments upon the statutes of 23 Eliz., 29 Eliz., or 3 Jacobi, against Protestants, for monthly absence from church, without any confession of the parties, or oath of witness against them, or made any presentments of them : contrary to the express letter of their oaths taken in a Court of Judgment, the course of the law of England, or any right reason : wherein is discoursed, whether any Protetant be concerned in that part of those laws? : the contrary is proved : as also whether a grand-jury's finding and indictment, be any evidence to a petit-jury? : the absurdness, and most pernicious consequents of which are detected, and the vengeance of God agaisnt false-swearing is declared / by one who prosecutes, as well for his sovereign lord the King of kings, as for the lives, liberties, and properties of all the subjects of England.</title>
                  <author>One who persecutes as well for his sovereign lord the King of kings as for the lives, liberties, and properties of all the subjects of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by L. Curtis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oaths --  England.</term>
               <term>Jury --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51262:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51262:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>TAM QUAM:</hi> OR AN ATTAINT Brought in the <hi>Supream</hi> Court of the <hi>King of Kings;</hi> upon the <hi>Statutes,</hi> Exod. 20. 7, 16. <hi>and</hi> Levit. 19. 12.</p>
            <p>Againſt thoſe Modern <hi>Jurors</hi> who have found any <hi>Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> upon the <hi>Statutes</hi> of 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 29 <hi>Eliz.</hi> or 3 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> againſt <hi>Proteſtants, for monthly Abſence from Church, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Confeſſion of the Parties,</hi> or <hi>Oath of Witneſs againſt them,</hi> or made any <hi>Preſentments of them.</hi> Contrary to the <hi>expreſs Letter of their Oaths</hi> taken in a <hi>Court of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the <hi>courſe of the Law</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> or any <hi>right Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is diſcourſed; <hi>Whether any Proteſtants be concerned in that part of thoſe Laws?</hi> the <hi>contrary is proved.</hi> As alſo whether a <hi>Grand-Jury's finding an Indictment,</hi> be any <hi>Evidence to a Petit-Jury?</hi> The abſurdneſs, and moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious <hi>Conſequents</hi> of which are detected, and the <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> of <hi>God</hi> alſo againſt <hi>Falſe-ſwearing</hi> is declared.</p>
            <p>By one who <hi>Proſecutes,</hi> as well for his <hi>Sovereign Lord</hi> the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> as for the <hi>Lives, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of all the Subjects of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Eccleſ. 5. 8.</bibl> 
               <p>If thou ſeeſt the Oppreſſion of the Poor, and violent perverting of Judgment and Juſtice in a Province, marvel not at the matter; for he that is higher than the higheſt, regardeth; and there be an higher than they.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>L. Curtis.</hi> 1683.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51262:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51262:2"/>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Miſchief ariſing to the Nation from the loſs of the Religion of Oaths. The Nature of an Oath. The Religion of an Oath loſt, by prophane and common Swearing, more by falſe Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, eſpecially in Judgment, whether by Jurors or Witneſſes. The Vengeance of God declared againſt it. The Diſcourſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to the Oaths of Jurors, and more eſpecially thoſe Oaths upon which they bring in Preſentments, and find Indictments againſt Proteſtants upon the Statutes <hi>23 Eliz. 29 Eliz.</hi> and <hi>3 Jacobi.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt other <hi>melancholick Conſiderations</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the Nation, which at this time <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> the Souls of thinking Men, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>there is a God that judgeth the Earth,</hi> there is none more ſad, or juſtly <hi>afflictive,</hi> than the Conſideration how much we have loſt the <hi>Religion of an Oath,</hi> and by that means broken the <hi>Ligament of Humane Society,</hi> and upon the point <hi>invalidated the Inſtitution of God for the end of all Strife:</hi> For according to the preſent uſe of <hi>Oaths</hi> they will be the end of <hi>no Strife,</hi> or at leaſt but a <hi>legal end;</hi> while no Man's Mind can acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſce in an <hi>Aſſertion</hi> or <hi>Promiſe</hi> confirmed by it. For how is it poſſible that the Mind of any ſhould acquieſce upon the <hi>Oaths</hi> of others, when he diſcerns how many there are that make no Conſcience of <hi>ſwearing</hi> what is <hi>falſe,</hi> or what is <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible they ſhould know to be true?</hi> Nor is there a greater Evidence of the ſtupid <hi>Atheiſm</hi> of a multitude of Perſons:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51262:3"/>
For, how can any think that thoſe believe there is a <hi>God,</hi> ſo <hi>omniſcient, juſt,</hi> and <hi>potent,</hi> as the <hi>Supream Being</hi> muſt be, who dare call him to be a <hi>Witneſs</hi> that they <hi>ſpeak Truth,</hi> or that <hi>they will do this or that thing,</hi> and <hi>challenge</hi> him to be their Judg in caſe they do it not, and deſire that He, and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Goſpel may do them no good if they do it not; and by and by dare to ſpeak what they either <hi>know to be falſe,</hi> or <hi>do not know to be true?</hi> It is not poſſible that Men indeed ſhould believe <hi>there is a God,</hi> and do any ſuch things. Every <hi>falſe Swearer</hi> muſt either declare himſelf to be <hi>ignorant</hi> of what he doth when he taketh an <hi>Oath,</hi> or to be an <hi>Atheiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It being more charitable to judg ſuch perſons <hi>ignorant,</hi> than to determine them abſolute <hi>Atheiſts.</hi> Charity will oblige every good Man to inſtruct his <hi>Relations</hi> or <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> in this great Point. All <hi>Divines</hi> agree that the nature of an Oath lies in the <hi>calling of God to witneſs,</hi> either to the truth of a Man's Aſſertion, or the Sincerity of his Heart as to his <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and his <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> in the <hi>performance</hi> of what he <hi>promiſeth.</hi> It was God's Ordinance, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 13. <hi>Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve him, and ſhalt Swear by his Name.</hi> Repeated again, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 20. <hi>To him thou ſhalt cleave, and Swear by his Name.</hi> Iſa. 65. 16. <hi>He that ſweareth in the Earth ſhall ſwear by the God of Truth.</hi> Jer. 12. 16. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs if they will diligently learn my ways, and ſwear by my Name, The Lord liveth.</hi> The Scriptures are full of Reproofs and Threatnings of and againſt any other <hi>Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> by <hi>thoſe that are no Gods;</hi> Jer. 5. 7. Joſh. 23. 7. Exod. 23. 13. Nor indeed is it reaſonable, that any other than the <hi>living God</hi> ſhould be invoked in <hi>Swearing,</hi> who elſe can know the correſpondency of our Hearts and Actions, or the ſincerity of our Intentions? Who elſe hath a power (in multitudes of caſes hidden from Men) to puniſh him who <hi>ſweareth falſely?</hi> So as an Oath by any other, than by the <hi>living God,</hi> is no <hi>ſecurity</hi> to our Neighbour. Hence all <hi>ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51262:3"/>
by any Creatures is <hi>prophane Swearing,</hi> and not only a <hi>violation of a Divine Command,</hi> but alſo of the very <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>end of an Oath,</hi> giving no <hi>ſecurity</hi> to the Perſon, for whoſe <hi>ſecurity</hi> of our Truth it is taken. Indeed it is no better than <hi>Idolatry,</hi> if Idolatry be a <hi>worſhiping of that for God which is no God:</hi> For Swearing is a <hi>Worſhip,</hi> tho indeed a leſs or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary piece of the Worſhip of God than <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Praiſe</hi> are.</p>
               <p n="3">3. An <hi>Oath</hi> being ſo grave a thing as a <hi>Divine Inſtitution.</hi> The <hi>Name of God being in it,</hi> and a <hi>ſolemn Invocation</hi> of him, to witneſs our Truth, <hi>eſſential</hi> to it, and the end of its <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> being to <hi>determine Strife,</hi> and to give our Neighbour the higheſt Security imaginable of our <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Common <hi>Reaſon</hi> will inſtruct Mankind, that it ought not to be uſed <hi>lightly</hi> and <hi>raſhly:</hi> for, beſides that ſuch uſe of an <hi>Oath</hi> tendeth to make it uſeleſs to its end; it is alſo an high <hi>prophanation of the holy and dreadful Name of the Lord our God.</hi> Which of us would not judg himſelf affronted, to have our Neighbours make uſe of any of our Names upon every <hi>light</hi> and <hi>trivial</hi> occaſion? or to be called on to <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> every ſilly and impertinent diſcourſe, or piece of Mens common Talk? Nor can that thing be any <hi>ſecurity</hi> to my Neighbour in any <hi>weighty Concern,</hi> which I lay to pawn at every <hi>Alehouſe,</hi> and expoſe at every <hi>Stall,</hi> much leſs that which hath proved to be no <hi>ſecurity</hi> a thouſand times, but made uſe of to ſeal a Lie. Beſides that ſuch common uſe of the <hi>Name of God,</hi> takes away all the <hi>Aw</hi> and <hi>Reverence</hi> of it; and who ſo thinks that any Man will make more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of an <hi>Oath</hi> in a <hi>Judicial Teſtimony,</hi> for, or againſt his Neighbour, than he doth in his <hi>common diſcourſe,</hi> muſt at leaſt think that the perſon who doth it, hath more <hi>Charity</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men, than <hi>Piety</hi> towards God, (which is very unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, conſidering that all <hi>Charity</hi> is the Daughter of <hi>Piety)</hi> or elſe he muſt have ſome <hi>odd thoughts of God,</hi> imagining him
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51262:4"/>
more <hi>ſevere</hi> in revenging a <hi>Wrong done to Man,</hi> than in the <hi>Vindication of his own Glory,</hi> whoſe Name is invoked as much in idle and <hi>common Swearing,</hi> as in a <hi>Judicial Testimony;</hi> and who is as much called to Witneſs, and whoſe Power is as much challenged to revenge a Falſhood in the one as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe. So that the many Precepts of God againſt common and ordinary Swearing in <hi>light</hi> and <hi>trivial matters,</hi> Exod. 20. 7. Deut. 5. 11. Mat. 5. 34. Jam. 5. 12. Levit. 19.12. are but conſonant to the <hi>common Reaſon of Mankind.</hi> And indeed the <hi>Judicial Swearing</hi> of a common Swearer in all his light and ordinary diſcourſe, will from hence appear to a delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Man but a very <hi>doubtful and ſuſpicious Evidence.</hi> For why ſhould I think the Man ſpeaks Truth any more, when in a Court he ſaith, <hi>So help me God, and his holy Goſpel;</hi> than when in a Tavern, Alehouſe or Market he ſaith, <hi>God damn me</hi> it is ſo, or <hi>I will do ſuch or ſuch a thing</hi> when I know <hi>it is not ſo,</hi> and am <hi>a witneſs to his not doing of it</hi> after ſuch Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations; ſo as in truth there could not be a <hi>juſter Law</hi> than to make <hi>common Swearers legally infamous;</hi> which might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably reduce Mens <hi>Tongues</hi> to a better <hi>decorum,</hi> and recover amongſt us the <hi>Religion of an Oath,</hi> upon the upholding the <hi>Religion</hi> of which depend all our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Properties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. A <hi>falſe ſwearing by the Name of the moſt high God,</hi> (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in Judgment) will eaſily from hence appear to be one of the <hi>higheſt Crimes,</hi> and <hi>daring pieces of Impudence,</hi> that a mortal Man can be guilty of. A <hi>Guilt</hi> incurr'd, not only when <hi>the thing</hi> we confirm by our Oaths <hi>is falſe,</hi> but when <hi>we do not know it to be true.</hi> And in <hi>promiſary Oaths,</hi> when we do not do the thing which we have ſworn to do. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſwear the Lord liveth, in Truth, in Righteouſneſs, and in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> Jer. 4. 2. This is the Law of God concerning an Oath; I muſt not call <hi>God to witneſs</hi> that <hi>a thing is true,</hi> and <hi>diſclaim any hopes in him,</hi> or <hi>deſire of help from him, or the Word of Salvation</hi> if it be not true, if <hi>the thing be falſe;</hi> or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51262:4"/>
unleſs I <hi>know it to be true:</hi> for I cannot ſay a thing is true, which doth not ſo appear to me. Nor muſt I call God to <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> that I will <hi>do ſuch or ſuch a thing;</hi> and <hi>diſclaim any hopes, or deſire of any benefit from him, or the Word of Salvation,</hi> if I do it not, and then not do it. Under the <hi>Levitical Law,</hi> (Lev. 5.4.) God indeed appointed a <hi>Treſpaſs-Offering</hi> for him that had <hi>ſworn to do Evil, or to do Good, if it were hid from him,</hi> confeſſing that <hi>he had ſinned in that thing;</hi> but in that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> was required in the caſe, and not <hi>Confeſſion</hi> only, but a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> the Sin of thoſe who <hi>ſwear falſly</hi> (tho ignorantly) is evident enough; and in that we read of no <hi>Sacrifice</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for thoſe that <hi>ſwear falſly,</hi> knowing thereof when they ſware, we may be aſſured that was a Guilt God did not expect from any of his People; or at leaſt, which he would not eaſily forgive, or <hi>purge by Sacrifice.</hi> And indeed what puniſhment can we ſuppoſe too great for that perſon, who ſhall dare to <hi>call God to Witneſs that he ſpeaketh Truth, when he knows it is a Lie,</hi> or <hi>doth not know that what he ſaith is true?</hi> Or, <hi>who dares to diſclaim all Benefit from God, or the Word of his Grace,</hi> if he doth not <hi>do this or that, and then doth it not?</hi> His Blood is upon his own head, if God ſtrikes this Man dead in the place; if he immediately throws him into the Bottomleſs-Pit, and concludes him under his Wrath to all Eternity, he doth but deal with him according to his own Prayer and Deſire. He hath asked no further Grace, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or Favour from God than according to the Truth of his Heart and Actions in ſuch or ſuch a thing wherein he hath wilfully ſuffered his Truth to fail; and that it may be not only in the higheſt contempt, and defiance of God, but may be to the no ſmall hurt and prejudice of his Neighbour, (tho that be much the lighter thing in the Caſe): for what can the Intereſt of a Man be conſidered with that of the Lord's Name and Glory? Out of his own mouth he is condemned; he hath ſpoken words againſt his own life. Whoſoever he be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51262:5"/>
that ſolemnly calleth God to be his Witneſs, <hi>That in ſuch or ſuch a thing he ſpeaketh the Truth,</hi> and <hi>that he ſhall or will do a thing in ſuch a manner,</hi> and <hi>diſclaimeth all Help or Salvation from God if he doth it not;</hi> and in the ſame matter, after ſuch a <hi>ſolemn Invocation</hi> of the Divine Name, and bold Challenge of the Divine Power, ſhall dare to affirm what he cannot ſay <hi>is Truth,</hi> or to do the quite contrary to what he hath promiſed with ſuch an Imprecation; what doth he do leſs than ſay, I value not what the Almighty God can do unto me; I deſie his Power, and deny his <hi>Being</hi> and Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Theſe things conſidered, we need not wonder at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi>'s telling us <hi>(Jer.</hi> 23. 10.) <hi>That becauſe of Swearing the Land mourneth;</hi> nor yet at the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> telling the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites from the Lord, <hi>That the Lord had a Controverſie with the Inhabitants of the Land; becauſe there was no Truth, nor Mercy, nor Knowledge of God in the Land. By [Swearing], and Lying, and Killing, and Stealing, and committing Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, they break out, and Blood toucheth Blood.</hi> Nor at the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zecheriah</hi>'s flying Roll, (Zech. 5.) <hi>twenty Cubits long, and ten Cubits broad,</hi> which v. 3. is expounded to be <hi>the Curſe that goeth over the face of the whole Earth; for every one that ſtealeth ſhall be cut off on this ſide according to it: and every one that [ſweareth] ſhall be cut off on that ſide, according to it. I will bring it forth, ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts, and it ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the houſe of the Thief, and into the houſe of him that [ſweareth falſly] by my Name; and it ſhall remain in the midſt of his houſe, and ſhall conſume it, with the Timber there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and the Stones thereof.</hi> Nor ſhall we need wonder if we ſee this Curſe entering into many houſes in this Nation, and remaining in them, until it hath conſumed the Timber there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and the Stones thereof. For <hi>ſwearing falſly</hi> is no leſs than a <hi>prophaning the Name of the Lord our God. Levit.</hi> 19. 12. a taking of his <hi>Name in vain,</hi> who hath ſaid, <hi>He will not hold</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51262:5"/>
                  <hi>him guiltleſs who taketh his Name in vain.</hi> And God hath ſaid, <hi>I will come near unto you in Judgment, and I will be a ſwift Witneſs againſt the Sorcerers, and againſt the Adulterers, and againſt the falſe Swearers,</hi> Mal. 3. 5.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It is true, the Law of <hi>England</hi> makes a diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>falſe-ſwearing,</hi> or <hi>forſwearing</hi> and Perjury, and will not allow <hi>forſwearing</hi> to be Perjury, puniſhable by the <hi>Statute-Law,</hi> unleſs it be <hi>malicious,</hi> and in a Caſe betwixt <hi>Party</hi> and <hi>Party.</hi> The Law of God maketh no ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction; <hi>falſe-ſwearing</hi> is the Crime which the Divine Law denounceth the <hi>Judgment of God againſt:</hi> And he that readeth my Lord <hi>Cook</hi>'s Chapter of <hi>Perjury</hi> in his <hi>Pleas of the Crown,</hi> will find, that according to the old Law of <hi>England,</hi> though one ſware what was Truth, but not what he <hi>could know to be true,</hi> was not puniſhable in other Courts, yet he was puniſhable in the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> of which he gives us an Inſtance in that Chapter: And without doubt ſo it ought to be, for I cannot truly ſwear that Thing to be, or to have been done, which I do not know is, or hath been done. In <hi>Palmer</hi>'s Reports, is an Inſtance of one indicted and puniſhed for ſwearing a Thing ſo, and ſo, (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was ſo) becauſe he did not know it to be ſo. <hi>Guide to Juries,</hi> p. 33.</p>
               <p n="7">7. It is not my deſign to diſcourſe this Theme in the latitude, but only ſo far as concerneth <hi>Jurors</hi> in the <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Aſſizes</hi> and <hi>Seſſions,</hi> and that only with reſpect to <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Caſes.</hi> Our Law was not ſo confident of twelve or 24 Men in a <hi>Grand Jury,</hi> or a <hi>Petit-Jury,</hi> but that it hath provided againſt <hi>falſe-ſwearing</hi> in them, by <hi>two Acts</hi> of <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taint:</hi> by the one, 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.21. proviſion is only made for <hi>the City of London;</hi> by the other, for the whole Nation, 23 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. 3. Which <hi>Statute</hi> alloweth, the Perſon wronged by an <hi>untrue Verdict,</hi> to bring an <hi>Attaint</hi> againſt the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons giving ſuch <hi>Verdict,</hi> if it amounted to the value of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51262:6"/>
                  <hi>forty Pounds,</hi> and recover of every one of them <hi>twenty Pounds, ten</hi> for the King, <hi>ten</hi> for himſelf; but this muſt be only in Caſes <hi>betwixt Party and Party.</hi> It ſeemeth a defect in our Law, that if the <hi>King</hi> be a Party, the <hi>Jury</hi> ſhall not be attainted; for every one will apprehend it very unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, that <hi>Jurors</hi> ſhould be <hi>attainted,</hi> and their <hi>Verdicts</hi> again be examined by 24 Men in an <hi>Attaint,</hi> where the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is a loſer <hi>forty Pounds or upwards;</hi> and that they ſhould be liable to no puniſhment for an untrue <hi>Verdict,</hi> where the Dammage amounteth to much more. I remember in a <hi>parallel Caſe</hi> of <hi>Perjury in a Witneſs,</hi> where the Law de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termineth no Indictment on the Statute ſhall lie, becauſe the Statute is reſtrained to Oaths between Party and Party, My Lord <hi>Cook</hi> determineth, that though no Indictment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stat. 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> will lie in the Caſe, yet an Indictment ſhall lie at <hi>Common Law;</hi> and that hath been often experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced; and that <hi>great Oracle of the Law</hi> gives an unanſwerable Reaſon for it, <hi>Becauſe it is not reaſonable that</hi> the <hi>King's Name, (who is the Fountain of Juſtice)</hi> ſhould <hi>patronize Injuſtice.</hi> Whether an <hi>Attaint</hi> at the <hi>Common Law</hi> doth not lie againſt <hi>Jurors</hi> bringing in <hi>falſe Verdicts,</hi> (which indeed is nonſenſe) though they find for the <hi>King,</hi> deſerves the ſtudy of <hi>Lawyers.</hi> Sure I am, my Lord <hi>Cook,</hi> in his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Perjury,</hi> gives us an account, That by the old Law of <hi>England, Jurors</hi> bringing in untrue <hi>Verdicts,</hi> were moſt ſeverely puniſh'd, <hi>by Impriſonment, ſeiſure of all their Eſtates, turning out their Wives and Children, pulling down their Houſes,</hi> and <hi>being made infamous,</hi> their <hi>Oaths never more to be admitted in any Court.</hi> This Law is ſurely not ſo extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, but ſome <hi>puniſhment</hi> yet remains for all ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, if once we could hit upon the <hi>Methods</hi> that ſhall bring them to it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. But my buſineſs is only to ſhew them, that there lies an <hi>Attaint</hi> againſt them in the <hi>Court of Heaven,</hi> the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51262:6"/>
of which is, not only <hi>the eternal damnation of their Souls,</hi> according to their own deſire in the <hi>Oath</hi> they take, but the <hi>Curſe of God entring into their Houſes, and abiding in them until it hath conſumed the Timber thereof, and the Stones thereof.</hi> Nor ſhall I meddle with all their <hi>Verdicts,</hi> only ſuch as they have brought in againſt <hi>diſſenting Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> upon the Statutes 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and 29 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and 3 <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi.</hi> This is the only Point I deſign to put in Iſſue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured, That if the Conviction of theſe Men upon thoſe Statutes, prove to be upon their <hi>falſe-ſwearing,</hi> it hath in it all the <hi>aggravations</hi> almoſt imaginable, being done in a <hi>Court of Juſtice,</hi> and iſſuing in the <hi>ruin</hi> of ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Perſons, and Families. Hoping alſo that if it ſo proves, thoſe who have urged, inſtructed, and taught them ſo to do, will reflect upon themſelves in time, and conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are not like to come under our Saviour's Cenſure, of being <hi>the leaſt in the Kingdom of God,</hi> for <hi>teaching</hi> (if not forcing) ignorant Souls to break the Commandment of God, and that in Matters, where his <hi>Glory,</hi> as well as the Good of their Neighbours, are moſt eminently concerned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51262:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Forms of the Oaths adminiſtred to Grand-Jurors, Petit-Jurors and Witneſſes, at the Aſſizes or General Quarter-Seſſions. The Preſentments of Grand-Juries upon the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Statutes; with the Form of the Indictments found, either by them or Petit-Juries. Their Method in proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Grand-Jurors by their Oath, can preſent nothing, but what they know to be Truth, either of their own Knowledg, or the Oaths of credible Perſons, but they muſt be forſworn. Petit-Jurors are forſworn, if they find without Evidence. The Law no where caſts the Proof upon the Party accuſed, but in this Caſe directs other Evidence expreſly. Grand-Juries finding an Indictment, no Evidence to the Petit-Jury of the Truth of it, proved by ſix Arguments. The pernicious Conſequents of the allowing them to be Evidence as a Grand-Jury. It confounds Accuſers and Evidence in ſome Caſes; Judges and Evidence in other Caſes. The Law allows it in no Caſe. Nor can Petit-Jurors, without being forſworn, find an Indictment upon no other Evidence.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THis Iſſue cannot be better tried, than <hi>by an enquiry into the Oaths taken by all Jury-Men,</hi> and then into the <hi>Indictment upon theſe Statutes;</hi> and <hi>laſtly, into the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence brought before them of the Fact.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Oath which every Perſon of <hi>Grand-Juries</hi> takes, is in this Form.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ſhall diligently inquire, and true Preſentment make, of all ſuch Things and Matters as ſhall be given you in</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51262:7"/>
                  <hi>Charge, or ſhall come to your knowledg concerning this preſent Service. The King's Counſel, and your Own, and your Fellows, you ſhall well and truly keep ſecret. You ſhall preſent nothing for Malice, Lucre, Ill-will; nor leave any thing unpreſented, for Love, Favour, or Affection, Reward, or any hopes thereof: but in all things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern this preſent Service, you ſhall preſent the Truth, the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth. So help you God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This every one of them promiſeth, and teſtifieth his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, by kiſſing the Book of God. I deſire it may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that the <hi>Oath</hi> ſaith not, You ſhall <hi>true Preſentment make of ſuch things</hi> as you <hi>think</hi> or <hi>ſuſpect,</hi> or <hi>preſume,</hi> but that <hi>ſhall come to your Knowledg.</hi> You ſhall preſent <hi>the Truth,</hi> not your Fancies or Surmiſes, and what you have no knowledg of, either from your perſonal certain Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, or by the <hi>Oaths</hi> of credible Perſons, <hi>and nothing but the Truth;</hi> that is, what ſhall <hi>come to your knowledg,</hi> either by the <hi>Oaths of credible Perſons,</hi> or <hi>from your own ſight,</hi> or <hi>obſervation;</hi> for nothing elſe can appear to a Grand-Jury-Man as Truth in Judgment.</p>
               <q>Every Member of a <hi>Petit-Jury</hi> takes this <hi>Oath.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ſhall well and truly try, and true deliverance make, between our Sovereign Lord the King, and the Priſoner, [or Perſon] at the Bar, according to your Evidence. So help you God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Witneſſes ſwear, <hi>They will ſpeak the Truth, the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51262:8"/>
Every <hi>Jury-Man,</hi> and Witneſs, in teſtimony of his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that Promiſory Oath, <hi>kiſſeth the Book;</hi> thereby only teſtifying, that he calleth <hi>God to Witneſs,</hi> that <hi>he will do that thing which is propounded to him,</hi> without Malice or Favour; and <hi>deſiring God, that he may receive no Mercy from him, nor benefit from his Goſpel, if he doth otherwiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Grand-Jury's Preſentment, according to theſe Statutes, muſt be, <hi>That ſuch a Perſon, for the ſpace of one or more Months, being of the Age of ſixteen Years and upward, did not repair to ſome Church, Ghappel, or uſual place of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer, but did forbear the ſame, having no lawful Let nor Impediment, contrary to the Statute made in the firſt Year of her Majeſty's Reign.</hi> They commonly run in a ſhorter Form; but they declare to the <hi>Clerk</hi> of the <hi>Aſſizes</hi> or <hi>Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> that they deſire they might be drawn up according to Form. Which is done by him, nothing <hi>material</hi> being omitted in the Form mentioned, nor added thereunto. This is found by the <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> at the next <hi>Aſſizes</hi> or <hi>Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> and being found by them, is without alteration tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the <hi>Petit-Jury,</hi> and by them found, or rejected, without any alteration.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I grant it poſſible, that there are ſeveral caſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Jury-Men</hi> may find ſuch an <hi>Inditement</hi> without <hi>falſe ſwearing.</hi> Admit they know that ſuch a Perſon were all thoſe days, <hi>in his own Houſe, or in ſome Neighbours Houſes,</hi> at an <hi>Ale-Houſe,</hi> or at an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful Meeting,</hi> or walking idly in the Fields, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or that any ſuch thing be ſworn before them, they may undoubtedly, yea and by their Oath are obliged to preſent him, or indict him: But if they know no ſuch thing from their <hi>own ſight or obſervation,</hi> nor from the <hi>Oath</hi> of Perſons whom they judg credible; That they who have called <hi>God to Witneſs,</hi> that they will preſent <hi>the Truth,</hi> and <hi>nothing but the Truth,</hi> that is <hi>come to their Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,</hi> may preſent any upon that Statute, or upon their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51262:8"/>
Oaths aver the <hi>Truth</hi> of any ſuch Indictment, is what no Learned and Sober <hi>Divine</hi> in the World dare aſſert. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet did any Divine aſſert, that it was no <hi>forſwearing</hi> a Man's ſelf for him to <hi>affirm upon Oath,</hi> what <hi>he did not know,</hi> either from his own ſight, or obſervation, or the credible Teſtimony of others aſſerting it upon their Oaths, (for no <hi>Jury</hi> ought to hear or regard any other Information). How impoſſible it is that any <hi>Grand-Jury-Man</hi> ſhould know that <hi>A. B.</hi> was <hi>neither at his Pariſh-Church, nor any other, any Sunday, or Holy-Day, for one or more Months,</hi> unleſs he knew that all ſuch Days he was at another place, is obvious to the meaneſt Underſtanding. If he doth not know it, he <hi>ſweareth falſly,</hi> in preſenting the Perſon for it upon that <hi>Oath</hi> which he hath taken to preſent <hi>the Truth,</hi> and <hi>nothing but the Truth.</hi> What he knoweth not, can be to him <hi>no Truth,</hi> much leſs can it be a thing <hi>come to his Knowledg.</hi> And I am ſure it is <hi>nothing given him in charge.</hi> None ever in his Wits, yet ſaid, that a thing which one only <hi>preſumes, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects,</hi> or <hi>thinks,</hi> is <hi>come to his Knowledg,</hi> or what he can aver to be Truth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is true, ſometimes <hi>Grand-Juries,</hi> only offer <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles Preſentments upon their Oaths,</hi> in which caſe much is to be ſaid in the Excuſe of <hi>Grand-Juries.</hi> It is then come to their knowledg, upon the <hi>Oaths</hi> of thoſe whom the Law judgeth credible Perſons; but ſuch Preſentmens uſe not to be of <hi>Perſons</hi> for <hi>not coming to their Pariſh-Church, nor any other,</hi> they only can ſpeak for <hi>their Pariſh-Church.</hi> Nor can any <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> bring in any ſuch Preſentments, but for abſence from their <hi>Pariſh-Church.</hi> If they add, <hi>nor to any other,</hi> they make the <hi>Act their</hi> own; or if it be added by any other who draws ſuch Indictment into Form, the next Grand-Jury cannot, without <hi>falſe-ſwearing, find it,</hi> unleſs they <hi>perſonally know it,</hi> or it be made good to them by one or more credible Oaths. If they do, they notoriouſly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51262:9"/>
the <hi>Oath</hi> they have taken, to preſent <hi>nothing but the Truth, and what cometh to their Knowledg;</hi> whatſoever is added to the firſt Preſentment, can be ſaid in no ſenſe to come to their <hi>Knowledg,</hi> if they do not know it <hi>perſonally,</hi> without <hi>new Oaths</hi> to confirm it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Theſe things conſidered, it will poſe the ſubtilleſt Divines in the World to excuſe Perſons ſerving upon <hi>Grand-Juries,</hi> from <hi>falſe-ſwearing,</hi> in theſe <hi>Preſentments</hi> or <hi>Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> who do not <hi>perſonally</hi> know the thing to be true which they preſent, or at leaſt know it from the <hi>Oaths of others</hi> taken before them: of whom alſo it is their Duty, according to their Oath, <hi>diligently to enquire</hi> upon what grounds they ſwear ſuch a thing, before they can true Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment make. Theſe things are ſo obvious, that it may juſtly amaze any underſtanding Perſon that any ſhould have any other apprehenſions. Nor certainly is it poſſible they ſhould, if Mens <hi>common Learning</hi> in their ordinary Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe had not baniſhed out of the World all <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of an Oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. For the <hi>Petit-Jury,</hi> they ſwear to make a <hi>true Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance according to their Evidence.</hi> So as the Truth or Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of their Oath dependeth upon the <hi>Evidence</hi> they have. It will poſe any Perſon to think what Evidence twelve Men can have, that another for all the <hi>Sundays</hi> and <hi>Holy-days</hi> in a <hi>Month, or more, hath not been at ſome Church or Chappel where Divine Service hath been, and having no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Let or Impediment.</hi> This every Member of a <hi>Petit-Jury,</hi> who findeth any Indictments of this Nature, doth, and muſt affirm, or there could be no <hi>Conviction.</hi> And he affirmeth it, after <hi>his ſolemn calling God to Witneſs,</hi> that in this caſe, he will <hi>affirm Truth,</hi> and that <hi>according to his Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> What Evidence is it poſſible ſuch a Jury ſhould have, but <hi>Confeſſion of the Party,</hi> or the <hi>Oath</hi> of ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who hath been with him all thoſe days in other Places,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51262:9"/>
any reaſonable Perſon may judg; and we ſhall ſee anon, that in this very Caſe of Abſence from Church, the Law of <hi>England</hi> alloweth no other <hi>Proof.</hi> And every <hi>Petit-Jury-Man,</hi> doth affirm this to be Truth upon no leſs than his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and deſireth that the God of Mercy, and his Holy Goſpel may <hi>ſo help him,</hi> as he hath acted truly, not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Suſpicions, Fears, or Belief, but according to his <hi>Evidence</hi> in ſaying, he is <hi>Guilty.</hi> Hath not (think we) the <hi>Clerk</hi> of the Court reaſon to part with theſe Juries after ſuch <hi>Verdicts,</hi> with the ſame Prayer or Complement, that he doth ſometime part with condemned Priſoners with,<hi>—and the Lord have Mercy upon your Souls?</hi> For not one Indictment of many hundreds of this nature, are found upon any ſuch <hi>Evidence,</hi> or indeed upon any <hi>Evidence</hi> at all, which is either ſuch in its own Nature, or according to the Law of <hi>England</hi> in all other Caſes, as alſo in this very Caſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Proofs ought to be <hi>clear,</hi> and <hi>perſpicuous,</hi> ſaith my <hi>Lord Cook;</hi> and it is impoſſible any thing ſhould be an Evidence, which doth not make the Thing clear and <hi>evident.</hi> Indeed none that uſeth to ſpeak Senſe, will call any thing leſs, <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> Now what is there can be imagined in Nature to make a <hi>matter of Fact evident</hi> to <hi>others,</hi> but either the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Party,</hi> or the <hi>Oath of Witneſs,</hi> or the <hi>perſonal knowledg of the Truth of it to the Perſons to whom it is ſo to be made evident?</hi> Thoſe that ſerve upon <hi>Grand-Juries,</hi> may, according to their Oaths, look upon the laſt, as an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for them ſufficient to preſent upon; that a <hi>Petit-Jury</hi> may, I never heard affirm'd: none of them can be <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>Judges</hi> in the <hi>Matter of Fact.</hi> The Law of <hi>England</hi> indeed alloweth another <hi>conviction</hi> in this Caſe, <hi>viz. In caſe a Perſon preſented, indicted, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, doth not appear in Perſon at the next Seſſions or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes, and put himſelf upon his Traverſe.</hi> The Reaſon is, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Law takes ſuch a Perſon to confeſs the Fact.</hi> And it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51262:10"/>
may be this is righteous enough, provided that ſuch perſons have <hi>Summons</hi> to appear, truly ſerved upon them. But if they have not, <hi>it is the higheſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs</hi> imaginable: For though the Law ſuppoſeth all his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Subjects to be preſent at <hi>Aſſizes</hi> and <hi>Seſſions,</hi> yet every one knows how impoſſible a thing it is that all <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women</hi> above ſixteen years of age ſhould ſo appear, and know what is done: Upon which account our Law ordereth <hi>Summons</hi> of the <hi>Party</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every <hi>Preſentment;</hi> and if the Party be not <hi>ſummoned</hi> to proceed againſt him, can be no Righteouſneſs; for <hi>our Law condemneth none</hi> before the <hi>Executioners</hi> of it <hi>have heard him ſpeak,</hi> or at leaſt given him an opportunity, that if it be not his own fault, they may hear him ſpeak for himſelf. Yet multitudes are thus Preſented, and Convicted, and great por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their Eſtates ſeized, who never ſo much as knew they were Preſented or Accuſed, till the <hi>Sheriff</hi> and <hi>Bayliffs</hi> come and make a Seiſure of their Eſtates, which certainly is in the <hi>Officers</hi> an <hi>Iniquity to be puniſhed by the Judge,</hi> and an <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs</hi> from which every one ought to be relieved: for tho the perſon's not appearing if he be ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned and <hi>proclaimed,</hi> and hath notice of ſuch <hi>Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> may be a ground of a Righteous Conviction; yet if he hath no ſuch Summons, or notice of ſuch Proclamation, no ſuch Conviction can be righteous. For it is the condemning a Perſon, before they have heard him ſpeak, or given him a liberty to ſpeak for himſelf, a thing abhorred by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, who had no more than the Light of Nature to guide them in the things which they ought to do, and avoid. But this is a digreſſion from my Argument.</p>
               <p n="8">8. There are ſome ſo abſurd in this caſe as to affirm <hi>there needeth no Evidence; it is a thing which cannot be proved. And if the Perſon preſented and indicted, cannot prove that within the time for which he is ſo preſented and endicted, he was at ſome Church or Chappel, and that during the time, and the whole time</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51262:10"/>
                  <hi>of Common Prayer, or had ſome lawful impediment, the Petit-Jury ought to find ſuch Indictment.</hi> The Abſurdities of this Aſſertion are ſo many, that it is not eaſie to number all of them; I will hint at ſome few.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) If the Oath adminiſtred to the Petit-Jury were, <hi>You ſhall well and truly try, and true deliverance make betwixt our Sovereign Lord the King, and the Perſon at the Bar, without any Evidence.</hi> Though it would be a ſtrange Oath for any to adminiſter, or take, yet it might excuſe the <hi>Petit-Jury</hi> from the infamous crime of <hi>falſe ſwearing,</hi> though they found ſuch Indictments. But their Oath being to find <hi>according to their Evidence,</hi> it is impoſſible to excuſe them, finding without <hi>any Evidence:</hi> for none ever called <hi>Silence, Evidence,</hi> nor yet the <hi>extorted Confeſſion</hi> of the Party. The <hi>Law of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> requireth no Man to ſpeak any thing to accuſe himſelf, nor to prove himſelf guiltleſs, unleſs ſome Attempts have been firſt made to prove him guilty, which he can diſprove.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Again, This Aſſertion <hi>obligeth every Subject of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to have Witneſſes ready to prove he was at Church, at leaſt one time within every</hi> 28 <hi>days throughout the year:</hi> if not, he may, it ſeems, be Preſented, Indicted, and ought to be found guilty. The Statute gives twelve months time to proſecute upon theſe Statutes; Suppoſe perſons preſented and indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for abſence the firſt 28 days in that year: how many thouſand of innocent perſons may not be able to bring Proof of their preſence at Church after eleven months, any one day within that month?</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) <hi>There is no ſuch Proceeding allowed in any other Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Cauſe.</hi> Is the Man indicted for Robbery, or Murder, bound to prove he was at another place, &amp; in another com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, at that time when the Murder or Robbery was done, before it be firſt proved to the Jury <hi>upon Oath,</hi> that he was at that time in that place where ſuch a fact was committed? I cannot underſtand but by <hi>theſe Mens Law</hi> the very ſame
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51262:11"/>
Perſons found guilty of this Crime, may, when they pleaſe be found guilty of <hi>Murder, robbing by the High Way,</hi> or any other <hi>Capital Crime;</hi> if this be ſufficient Evidence to the <hi>Petit-Jury,</hi> that the Party accuſed having no Evidence againſt him, yet ſhall not acquit himſelf by proving the Place where he was at that Time, which after nine or ten Months, who is able to do? And theſe very <hi>Jury-men,</hi> who are ſo liberal of their Souls, as to find <hi>without Evidence</hi> in theſe Caſes, may one day, by God's righteous Retaliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, find themſelves thus dealt with.<hi>—Nec Lex eſt juſtior ulla. Quàm necis artifices arte perire ſuâ.</hi> To allow Perſons guilty of a Crime, without any other Evidence, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not, or perhaps cannot acquit themſelves by proving Circumſtances of Time and Place where they were, after 3, 5, 6, 10 Months time, (having no proſpect of ſuch an Accuſation) is a thing which may prove of moſt fatal Conſequence to every Mother's Child in the Nation.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) Yet if the Law of <hi>England</hi> (which alloweth it in no other Caſe) did, <hi>by any Clauſes</hi> in it, allow this to be a <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Evidence,</hi> in this ſomething might be ſaid. The Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Power may be allowed, when themſelves create a Crime, to ſet down what ſhall be <hi>Evidence of that Crime:</hi> But doth any of the <hi>Statutes,</hi> made in this Caſe, ordain any ſuch thing? Either the Statute 23, or 29 <hi>Eliz.</hi> or that 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> Nay, the <hi>Statute</hi> determineth the quite contrary, and that for this <hi>Crime</hi> of not <hi>coming to ſome Church.</hi> And that where the Puniſhment cannot exceed 4<hi>s.</hi> it ſaith,<hi>—<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon proof made of ſuch default, by confeſſion of the Party, or Oath of Witneſs,</hi> 3 Jacobi 4. Now will not the Law of <hi>England,</hi> in this Caſe, allow ſo little a ſum as 3 or 4 <hi>s.</hi> to be taken from any Subject, without either the accuſed Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's <hi>confeſſion of his Fault,</hi> or <hi>Oath of Witneſs.</hi> And ſhall any, pretending to <hi>know</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> impoſe upon a <hi>Jury</hi> to believe? Or ſhall any reaſonable Man that can but read,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51262:11"/>
be ever made to believe, that there need no Proof, no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but they muſt find the Indictment for 20 <hi>l.</hi> or it may be 200 <hi>l.</hi> (according to the number of the Months) eſpecially when the conſequence of their finding it will be, the Party's paying of 240 <hi>l.</hi> every Year after it, or loſing all his Goods, and two thirds of his real Eſtate, or lying in Priſon all his Life, unleſs the Party accuſed can prove him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Guiltleſs, and this after that ſuch Jury-Men have called God to Witneſs, they will give in their <hi>Verdict</hi> according <hi>to their Evidence:</hi> And the Law hath in this particular Crime made other <hi>Evidence</hi> neceſſary, and no where dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or allowed any ſuch thing, as the accuſed Perſons not clearing himſelf for Evidence. Do ſuch <hi>Jury-men</hi> believe <hi>there is a God,</hi> or expect any thing from this God, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from his Goſpel, when they have dared God to ſhew them no Mercy, if they do not do that, the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to which they do in an hours time? Will any Divine ſay theſe Men are not deſperately <hi>forſworn?</hi> Let any of them bring their Pleas, and let us ſee if they can ſpeak ſenſe in the Caſe; let them produce their Divines, that dare juſtify this not to be <hi>falſe-ſwearing,</hi> and the moſt <hi>abominable forſwearing,</hi> to the <hi>prejudice of their Brother,</hi> as well as <hi>the moſt impudent pollution</hi> and <hi>prophanation</hi> of the moſt holy and dreadful Name of God; and what wickedneſs may be preſumed they will ſtartle at, who in ſuch a degree proclaim they have no <hi>fear of God before their eyes,</hi> nor any belief of the <hi>Being, Power, Omniſcience, Truth,</hi> or <hi>Juſtice</hi> of God in their Hearts.</p>
               <p n="9">9. But they will ſay, The <hi>Petit-Jury hath Evidence: for the finding of the Indictment by the Grand-Jury, is ſufficient Evidence to the Petit-Jury.</hi> This new Notion is ſo falſe in it ſelf, and of ſo dangerous Conſequence, as it perfectly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verteth the whole Law of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Criminal Cauſes,</hi> and deſtroyeth one of the greateſt pieces of the <hi>Engliſh Liberty.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:51262:12"/>
               <p n="1">1. It is a fundamental Point in our Government, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be by Parliament, <hi>No Man's Life ſhall be touched, but by the Judgment of</hi> 24 <hi>Men;</hi> twelve of which make the <hi>Grand-Inqueſt,</hi> and are the Jury to <hi>inquire</hi> of Facts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of any are accuſed; twelve make the <hi>Petit-Jury</hi> for <hi>trial</hi> of the Iſſue. None can, at Aſſizes or Seſſions for their Life, or any part of their Eſtate, be put upon trial before the <hi>Grand-Inqueſt</hi> hath found the <hi>Indictment</hi> to be a true Bill. So as it is impoſſible that the <hi>Grand-Jury,</hi> as a <hi>Grand-Jury,</hi> ſhould be any Evidence to the <hi>Petit-Jury;</hi> for they have no <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Witneſſes</hi> adminiſtred to them, they are only ſworn to <hi>enquire,</hi> and to make a <hi>true Preſentment to the Court.</hi> If any Perſons know any thing of their perſonal knowledg, they may leave their capacity of <hi>Grand-Jury-Men,</hi> and come down, and give their Oaths in Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Petit-Jury,</hi> and may be Witneſſes; but as a <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> they can be no <hi>Evidence,</hi> nor have they any Oath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to them to that purpoſe, nor can the <hi>Petit-Jury</hi> propound any Queſtions to them, (a liberty allowed them as to all their <hi>Evidence):</hi> to make a <hi>Grand-Jury,</hi> Evidence, is to allow the Perſons to be <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Witneſſes;</hi> a thing never heard of in any juſt Court. The Work of Witneſſes is to prove a Fact; the Work of Judges, is to <hi>determine,</hi> according as the <hi>proof</hi> is made.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This were to make <hi>Petit-Juries perfectly needleſs,</hi> and of no uſe: for if the Grand-Juries finding an Indictment be Proof ſufficient, Reaſon will tell us, they are the fitteſt Men to <hi>determine the Fact,</hi> being ordinarily both a <hi>greater number,</hi> and Men of more <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and of <hi>better Quality</hi> than thoſe who appear on <hi>Petit-Juries:</hi> And if <hi>Petit-Juries</hi> have no power to bring in <hi>Not Guilty</hi> as a <hi>Verdict</hi> upon <hi>any Indictment</hi> by them found, they are perfectly of no uſe at all. Thus this ſeems a new Art to deprive the Subjects of all Trials by Juries.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51262:12"/>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Grand-Juries</hi> who find theſe Indictments, <hi>find them of courſe, ordinarily,</hi> without the leaſt proof of the truth of them, and know no more, than that a former <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> upon their Oaths made ſuch <hi>Preſentments,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true or falſe, is ſtill left to a Proof before the <hi>Petit-Jury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>Indictments,</hi> as they come to the <hi>Petit-Jury,</hi> have ordinarily more in them, than the Preſentments of the firſt <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> in the Caſe. The firſt <hi>Grand-Jury,</hi> either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth upon ſome of their own <hi>particular Knowledg</hi> of the <hi>Thing,</hi> or upon ſome <hi>Conſtable's Preſentment</hi> brought into them: let it be the one or the other, they are only <hi>for not coming to their Pariſh Church.</hi> No Conſtables will upon their Oaths preſent more; nor can it be preſumed of any <hi>Grand-Jury-Man,</hi> becauſe it is impoſſible for them to know, that they neither came <hi>to their own, nor to any other.</hi> Theſe words, <hi>Nor unto any other Church,</hi> which are eſſential words to the Charge, upon the truth of which the heavy Penalty lieth, are put in by the <hi>Clerks,</hi> who draw up the <hi>Indictments</hi> in Form, and neither ſworn before, or to <hi>one Grand-Jury</hi> or <hi>another.</hi> So as of them there is not the <hi>leaſt Evidence</hi> to the <hi>Petit-Jury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Nor is it reaſonable that the finding of an Indictment by a <hi>Grand-Jury,</hi> which is formed upon a <hi>Preſentment</hi> by a former <hi>Grand-Jury,</hi> ſhould be allowed as the <hi>leaſt Evidence of the Truth of the Fact</hi> contained in the ſaid <hi>Indictment;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Grand-Juries,</hi> tho' by their <hi>Oath</hi> they are bound to <hi>preſent the Truth,</hi> and <hi>nothing but the Truth,</hi> and what is <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them in Charge,</hi> and <hi>ſhall come to their Knowledg,</hi> yet (with what faithfulneſs to their <hi>Oaths</hi> deſerves their ſecond Thoughts, and may hereafter come to be examined) take upon them to preſent what <hi>none of them doth know,</hi> nor <hi>can know;</hi> nor is made, by the <hi>Oaths</hi> of any, to appear to them, but what they <hi>ſuſpect,</hi> or have heard from <hi>others,</hi> not upon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51262:13"/>
Oath, counting that a thing <hi>comes to their knowledg,</hi> tho they have catched it from the <hi>tittle tattle of the Town,</hi> or the mouths of any malicious Perſons; not conſidering that they alſo ſwear to preſent <hi>the Truth,</hi> and <hi>nothing but the Truth,</hi> and have diſclaimed all hopes of Salvation, if they do otherwiſe than according to ſuch an Oath. Many of them have been ſo eaſily deluded, to invoke God's Vengeance upon themſelves, as to think that they may do it upon a <hi>common Fame,</hi> and that not proved before them neither; nay more, that they may do it, though ſome of themſelves know the contrary to ſuch Preſentment or Indictment; and put the Perſons to 40<hi>s. charge</hi> at <hi>Seſſions,</hi> or 7 or 8 <hi>l.</hi> charge at the Aſſizes to <hi>clear themſelves;</hi> and very often it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that ſuch Preſentments are notoriouſly falſe. Now that a <hi>Petit-Jury</hi> ſhould take ſuch <hi>Preſentments,</hi> or <hi>Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> for <hi>Evidence,</hi> is a thing ſo obviouſly contrary to Senſe and Reaſon, as well as their Oath which they take, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing need be ſaid againſt it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>It is expreſly contrary to the Law of</hi> England, <hi>in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Cauſes <hi>Criminal, That the Preſentments of Officers, who preſent</hi> ex officio, <hi>ſhould go for Evidence:</hi> Nor doth either the <hi>Common,</hi> or <hi>Statute-Law of</hi> England, direct it any where in this Caſe. This is to make the <hi>Accuſers,</hi> Evidence, and to confound <hi>Accuſers</hi> and <hi>Witneſſes.</hi> Whereas, <hi>Si ſatis ſit accuſari nullus erit innocens;</hi> It was all our Fore-father's Opinion, that none could be innocent, if the Accuſers might be allowed for <hi>Evidence.</hi> If the <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> do but deliver in the <hi>Preſentments,</hi> or <hi>Indictments</hi> of others, they are in that caſe conſidered as <hi>Judges</hi> in the Matter of Fact, averring their <hi>charitable belief</hi> that ſuch <hi>Preſentments</hi> are true. If the <hi>Preſentment</hi> ariſeth <hi>originally</hi> from themſelves, they are but the <hi>Accuſers,</hi> and in that capacity can be no Evidence; to ſay that <hi>Common Fame</hi> is the Accuſer in the Caſe, when that <hi>Common Fame</hi> is a mere aerial thing, ſuck'd
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51262:13"/>
in by ſome or other of the Grand-Jury, and not juſtified to the whole Body of the <hi>Grand Jury, vivâ Voce,</hi> is but to dignify a <hi>Chimera.</hi> There can be no <hi>Common Fame,</hi> without a <hi>multitude</hi> to report it; which I preſume <hi>Grand-Juries</hi> have not coming to them upon that Errand; and if they had, they muſt be ſworn in Court, before (by the Law of <hi>England)</hi> they can come near to make the <hi>Common Fame.</hi> In all ſuch Caſes therefore, to make a <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> an <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> to the <hi>Petit-Jury,</hi> is to make <hi>Accuſers, Evidence,</hi> the Conſequents of which I leave to every Man of ſenſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If Malice did not out-law the Reaſon of <hi>Jurors,</hi> who find <hi>Indictments</hi> on no other Evidence than this, they would conſider, <hi>Hodie mihi, cras tibi, What you make the Lot of others to day, may be yours to morrow.</hi> A <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> may find againſt you an Indictment for <hi>treaſonable words</hi> you never ſpake, <hi>Heretical Opinions or Speeches, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Theft, Burglary.</hi> In three or four of theſe Caſes it is very ordinary for <hi>Grand-Juries</hi> to find, upon <hi>ſlighty Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> becauſe <hi>the Good of the Publick is concerned.</hi> If the <hi>Petit-Jury</hi> need no other Evidence, every Subject's <hi>Life, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> is at the Mercy of every <hi>Villain.</hi> If any will ſay, that in ſuch Caſes there muſt be further <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> brought to the <hi>Petit-Jury;</hi> I ask, Why? <hi>Evidence</hi> is <hi>Evidence,</hi> I hope in one Cauſe as well as in another, except the Statute-Law directs otherwiſe, which I am ſure it doth not. Beſides, that <hi>Grand-Juries</hi> often find Indictments (where the Publick Peace and Government is concerned) upon very ſlight <hi>Evidence,</hi> becauſe they know they cannot be convicted without other more <hi>full</hi> and <hi>particular Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> So that to allow their finding the Indictment for <hi>Evidence</hi> to found a Conviction upon, is the greateſt Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs imaginable. Upon the Trial of my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> my Lord Chief Juſtice told the <hi>Grand-Jury,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:51262:14"/>
                  <q>That that which was referred to them to conſider, was, Whether upon the Evidence ſhould be given to them, there be any Reaſon or Ground for the King to call theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to an account: if there be probable ground, it is as much as you are to enquire into. You are not to judg the Perſons: but for the Honour of the King, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of the Matter, it is not thought fit by the Law, that Perſons ſhould be accuſed and indicted, where there is no colour nor ground for it, where there is no kind of ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of a Crime, nor reaſon to believe that the thing can be proved. It is not for the King's Honour to call Men to an account in ſuch Caſes; therefore you are to enquire Whether that that you hear, be any Cauſe or Reaſon for the King to put the Party to anſwer it. You do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, nor is there ſuch a ſtrict enquiry to be made by you, as by others that are ſworn to a Fact or Iſſue. A pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Cauſe, or ſome Ground, that the King hath to call thoſe Perſons to anſwer for it, is enough <hi>(Gentlemen)</hi> for you to find the <hi>Bill,</hi> it is as much as is by Law required.</q>
               </p>
               <p>From this great <hi>Oracle</hi> of <hi>Law,</hi> may eaſily be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered;</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That any probable Ground or Reaſon that the King hath to queſtion a Perſon for ſuch a Fact, any kind of ſuſpicion of the Crime, and that it may be proved, is enough for a Grand-Jury.</hi> 2. <hi>That the Grand-Juries Work is not to condemn, nor to make ſo ſtrict an inquiry, as the Jury for Trial, who are ſworn to a Fact, or Iſſue.</hi> Add now to this, the common ſayings of ſome little Country Lawyers at a <hi>Seſſions Cuſhion. That the Grand-Juries finding the Indictment</hi> is <hi>Evidence enough.</hi> And affirming to Juries, <hi>That this is</hi> Law; and obſerve what follows.</p>
               <p>Then a ſuſpicion that a Man hath <hi>ſtollen an</hi> Horſe, or a <hi>probable</hi> Ground that the King hath reaſon to queſtion a Man for a <hi>Murder,</hi> without any ſtrict inquiry into the thing,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51262:14"/>
whether it be ſo or no, is ground enough by Law for a <hi>Petit-Jury</hi> to find a Man guilty of the <hi>Theft,</hi> or of the <hi>Murder.</hi> But this was not my Lord Chief Juſtice his ſenſe, who tells us the <hi>Jury for Trial, who are ſworn to a Fact or Iſſue, muſt make a ſtrict enquiry,</hi> as to which he conceiveth a <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> not concerned; and therefore what they find is no <hi>Evidence</hi> to a <hi>Petit-Jury.</hi> But thoſe that find an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment upon no other <hi>Evidence,</hi> are apparently forſworn, bringing in their <hi>Verdict</hi> not according to their <hi>Evidence,</hi> but without any <hi>Evidence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A ſhort Diſquiſition, whether the Statutes of <hi>23 Eliz. 29 Eliz.</hi> and <hi>3 Jacobi,</hi> concern any Proteſtants. The Arguments for their concern in them propounded, and anſwered, and found too light to ballance three great Arguments to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: which are propounded and enlarged upon.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. I Know it is Forreign to this Diſcourſe to debate the <hi>Queſtion, Whether thoſe Statutes of</hi> 23 Eliz. 29 Eliz. 3 Jac. <hi>do in all the branches of them concern Proteſtants, or no,</hi> particularly <hi>in thoſe Branches which relate to coming to, or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting from Church?</hi> Great Lawyers are divided in their Opinions as to it: thoſe who think they do, urge,</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) <hi>The general words, every Perſon,</hi> and the mention of <hi>Recuſants</hi> ſometimes, without the addition of <hi>Popiſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) The <hi>reference of thoſe Statutes</hi> to the Stat. 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. in which they ſay <hi>Proteſtants</hi> as well as <hi>Papiſts</hi> are moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly concerned.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) The <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> which is within the <hi>Stat.</hi> 3 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> and may be given to any <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51262:15"/>
None of which can be determined, <hi>concludent,</hi> in the Caſe, after the fore-going part of a Statute hath declared the Reaſons and Grounds for the making of that Law, <hi>viz.</hi> The bringing in of <hi>Popiſh Bulls,</hi> ſeducing People to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Religion,</hi> and determined ſuch Perſons guilty of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, (Crimes which no Proteſtant can be guilty of) tho' it follows as a means to prevent theſe things, that <hi>every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> that for a Month ſhall <hi>abſent himſelf from his Pariſh-Church, ſhall forfeit</hi> 20 <hi>l.</hi> Yet certainly it is a fair Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it to reſtrain that general Term, to that <hi>ſort of Perſons</hi> which alone are mentioned in all the preceding part of the <hi>Act.</hi> Nor certainly in any juſt <hi>conſtruction,</hi> can <hi>general words,</hi> whether <hi>Affirmative</hi> or <hi>Negative,</hi> have more extent in <hi>one Statute</hi> than in another. In the late Act for <hi>the Sabbath,</hi> made for the keeping that Holy Day from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation; and an higher end cannot be, God having made it the <hi>4th Commandment</hi> in the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> and denominated all <hi>Religion</hi> from it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 4. there is this clauſe,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Provided alſo, That no Perſon or Perſons, upon the Lord's Day, ſhall ſerve, or execute, or cauſe to be ſerved or executed <hi>any</hi> Writ, Proceſs, <hi>Warrant,</hi> Order, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Decree, (except in Caſes of Treaſon, Felony, or breach of the Peace) but that the ſervice of <hi>every</hi> ſuch Writ, Proceſs, <hi>Warrant,</hi> Order, Judgment, or Decree, ſhall be void, to all intents and purpoſes whatſoever. And the Perſon or Perſons ſo ſerving, or executing the ſame, ſhall be as liable to the Suit of the Party grieved, and to anſwer Dammages to him for doing thereof, as if he or they had done the ſame without any Writ, Proceſs, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, Order, Judgment, or Decree.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here are no leſs than three <hi>general terms;</hi> nor is there one Line in the Act excluding <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from the <hi>benefit of this Act,</hi> nor more authoriſing the Service of <hi>Warrants</hi> upon them for Meetings, than upon any others. It is true, the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51262:15"/>
                  <hi>Act againſt Conventicles,</hi> gives a further liberty; but it hath always held a Rule in Law, <hi>That latter Laws abrogate ſuch as were before, if contrary to them.</hi> Neither doth this Act <hi>abrogate</hi> it further than concerneth the <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> (the better Sanctification of which, was the deſign of the Act). Beſides, <hi>were not the former Laws which gave Liberty to Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Men on any Days, abrogated by this Act, ſo far forth as concerned that Point?</hi> Yet multitudes of <hi>Juſtices</hi> have ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted theſe general terms, that <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have no bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by it in this point, <hi>Warrants</hi> are yet executed on them, and their Doors broken open by Warrants, on theſe days. So, as it ſeems, <hi>general words</hi> in Statutes, ſhall comprehend <hi>diſſenting Proteſtants,</hi> where they will ſerve to do them miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, but not where they may do them kindneſs. But this is a Queſtion not yet decided (that I have heard of) by my <hi>Lords the Judges,</hi> as having not come judicially before them and the <hi>Juſtices.</hi> And others who have adventured thus far to make <hi>Blots,</hi> may ſome of them live to ſee them hit. General words are certainly every where of equal extent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor is the reference to the Statute of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. a proof, that all concerned in that Statute, are alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Statute of 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> for it is mentioned only as <hi>directive of the manner how Perſons ſhould go to Church, and there behave themſelves:</hi> How doth it from thence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that all who do not go, ſhould be puniſhed by a like Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, becauſe all are obliged to go to Church in the ſame Order, and to behave themſelves there in the ſame decent manner? Nor is the <hi>third Argument</hi> of more value, for there is nothing more ordinary than to find <hi>heterogeneous</hi> things in the ſame <hi>Statute Law.</hi> Nor will it follow, That the Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for <hi>not coming to Church,</hi> in the Statute 3 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> concern <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> in it doth, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when moſt Clauſes in that Act expreſs <hi>Popiſh Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants.</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51262:16"/>
But the Clauſes concerning that <hi>Oath,</hi> expreſly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>any Perſons</hi> 18 <hi>Years of Age, whether indicted or convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of Recuſancy, or no.</hi> But thoſe who make this Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhould alſo conſider that it is by the Act 7 <hi>Jacobi</hi> 6. that the Oath of Allegiance in 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> is given to Proteſtants, not by the Act. 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Arguments</hi> being no ſtronger for <hi>Proteſtants Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment</hi> in thoſe Acts, let us ſee what can be ſaid to prove <hi>they are not concerned in them.</hi> I do not pretend to ſo good an acquaintance with Records: But if it doth appear, 1. that for <hi>threeſcore Years after the making the Act</hi> 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> it was never put in <hi>Execution</hi> upon any but known and profeſſed <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> it is certain a greater Argument to prove that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are not within it in any due Conſtructions, than any can bring to prove they are. 2. I am ſure, if <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> though <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> be <hi>within thoſe Acts,</hi> they are, <hi>by the Statute Law of</hi> England, in a far worſe caſe, and expoſed to much higher Penalties, for not <hi>going to Church, and going to Meetings,</hi> than profeſſed <hi>Papiſts</hi> are: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides they are in all points made equal with them, as to the Stat. 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 29 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and 3 <hi>Jacobi;</hi> They are further in danger of the Stat. 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> (out of which Papiſts are in terms excepted); According to which <hi>Statute, Proteſtants,</hi> (and none but they) for theſe Crimes may be forced to <hi>abjure the Realm,</hi> or to <hi>die like Felons.</hi> I would gladly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, from any Man of ſenſe, to what purpoſe the Parliament 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> ſhould make ſo ſevere a Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> upon that little <hi>freak</hi> (the effect of a melancholick Deliration only) of <hi>Hacket, Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinger,</hi> and <hi>Arthington;</hi> if they had thought they had been included in the Acts of 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> made but twelve Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or of 29 <hi>Eliz.</hi> made but ſix Years before? Was not the loſing 260 <hi>l.</hi> a Year, a ſufficient Puniſhment for any thing they had ſhewed themſelves guilty of? Or was it judged
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51262:16"/>
puniſhment enough for Papiſts; for the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who had attempted to <hi>poiſon, to ſtab the Queen,</hi> to <hi>invade her</hi> by an <hi>invincible Armado,</hi> to raiſe up <hi>Rebellion</hi> in the Nation, and not enough for <hi>Proteſtants?</hi> Can we judg that any <hi>Engliſh Parliament</hi> in thoſe days could ſo judge? The Act of 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> was made upon the Papiſts filling the Land with <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> from the <hi>Engliſh Seminaries</hi> at <hi>Doway, Rhemes,</hi> and <hi>Rome;</hi> their <hi>publiſhing of Books</hi> to ſtir up <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in</hi> England, <hi>declaring that the Pope, and the King of</hi> Spain, <hi>had conſpired that</hi> England <hi>ſhould be made a Prey:</hi> And the woful ſtir then made by thoſe active <hi>Jeſuits, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> and <hi>Parſons. Campian, Sherwin, Kerby,</hi> and <hi>Briant,</hi> were taken the Year before, <hi>Anno</hi> 1581. This Act paſſed 1582. The 29 <hi>Eliz.</hi> was 1588, when we were invaded by the <hi>King of</hi> Spain<hi>'s invincible Armado;</hi> and ſix Years before <hi>Campian,</hi> the <hi>Head of that Faction,</hi> had openly declared, that in caſe of ſuch an <hi>Invaſion,</hi> he would <hi>take part with them againſt the Queen.</hi> The Act 3 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> came forth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Powder-Plot.</hi> I appeal to any Man of ordinary ſenſe, whether he can think that the <hi>Parliaments</hi> of thoſe Times, ever intended to put <hi>Proteſtants</hi> into a far worſe condition than <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which they apparently are, if theſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes equally concern them as well as Papiſts, and they then were liable to the Act 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> out of which <hi>Papiſts</hi> are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly excepted.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Further yet; I do very well know that <hi>Votes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> repeal no <hi>Laws,</hi> much leſs have the <hi>force</hi> of <hi>Laws</hi> in them, nor are to be mentioned in <hi>legal Pleas:</hi> But the <hi>Queſtion</hi> here is not, <hi>whether theſe Acts be of force or no?</hi> It is on all hands granted that they are; but <hi>what</hi> is the <hi>true ſenſe and meaning of them?</hi> And (as to that, under cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection) I think a great deference is to be given to the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Judgment declared in them, the far greater part of all the graveſt and moſt famous Lawyers of <hi>England</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:51262:17"/>
being generally in every <hi>Convention, or Seſſion of Parliament.</hi> It was, as I remember, either in the latter end of the Year 1677, or the beginning of the Year 1678, that upon the <hi>Petition</hi> of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> (at that time ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) firſt took notice, That the Laws made principally againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> were executed <hi>princially</hi> upon <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and appointed a <hi>Committee,</hi> who ſpent a great deal of time in examining the Returns of <hi>Convictions</hi> made upon thoſe <hi>Statutes</hi> into the Office, and applied themſelves to his <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> for favour to his <hi>Proteſtant Subjects</hi> as to thoſe Laws. About the middle of the Year 1678, the horrid <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> was diſcovered; from <hi>Michaelmas</hi> that Year, till <hi>Decemb.</hi> 30. the <hi>Parliament</hi> had enough to do to ſearch into the <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> and they had made but little <hi>progreſs</hi> in it when they were Prorogued, which was <hi>Decemb.</hi> 30. and ſoon after Diſſolved. The next <hi>Parliament</hi> began <hi>March</hi> 6. 1678/9, and ſat until <hi>May</hi> 27.1679. their whole time was alſo ſpent in a further <hi>diſcovery of that Helliſh Plot.</hi> All this while I met with no Declarations of the <hi>Parliament's</hi> mind or ſenſe in the caſe of thoſe <hi>Acts:</hi> Nor (as I believe) were there any <hi>complaints</hi> of any <hi>proſecutions</hi> of <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> upon any of thoſe <hi>Statutes.</hi> The next <hi>Parliament</hi> began <hi>Octob.</hi> 21. and held unto <hi>Jan.</hi> 10. 1680. By this time the <hi>Popiſh Party</hi> had a little recovered their Courage, and began to <hi>defame</hi> the very Report of a <hi>Popiſh Plot.</hi> They had eight months before began to <hi>ſham</hi> it, tho' with very ill ſucceſs: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time they had began to divert the <hi>proſecution</hi> of it, by obtaining of their Friends (who would be thought <hi>Proteſtants)</hi> every where to proſecute <hi>Diſſenters</hi> upon thoſe Statutes. The <hi>Parliament</hi> that ſat down <hi>Octob.</hi> 21.1680. had intelligence of it. The Term before <hi>Eſtreats</hi> were given out upon all <hi>Convictions</hi> upon thoſe Statutes; but with <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Inſtructions,</hi> from the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of the <hi>Treaſury,</hi> to leavy the <hi>Forfeitures</hi> upon <hi>none but known Popiſh Recuſants,</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:51262:17"/>
which 'tis likely that in many Counties the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> obſerved. In others 'tis certain they did not, but levied them equally, if not principally upon <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> but were inforced to refund ſome of them, and for a great while after this, upon a <hi>Certificate</hi> into the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> that the Perſons were <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> and had taken the <hi>Teſt,</hi> proceedings againſt them, by order out of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> were ſtaid. This is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have proceeded from his Majeſty's Goodneſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with the deſires of his Parliament, in the Caſe of the <hi>Quakers.</hi> The <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> which ſat in the <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Parliament, Octob.</hi> 21. 1680. had ſat but a Month and two or three odd days, before they came to this <hi>Vote,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out one Man's contradiction, in <hi>Nov.</hi> 1680.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Reſolved, <hi>nemine contradicente,</hi> That it is the Opinion of this Houſe, that the <hi>Acts of Parliament</hi> made in the Reigns of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> againſt <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Recuſants,</hi> ought not to be extended to <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Accordingly, they made their Application to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> by the Members of their Houſe, which were of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's moſt <hi>Honourable Privy Council,</hi> beſeeching him, <hi>That all the Proteſtant Diſſenters proſecuted upon thoſe Acts, might be diſcharged, without paying any Fees; and that he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend this Buſineſs to the Judges.</hi> Upon the <hi>26th</hi> of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1680. we find it thus in the <hi>Votes,</hi> under the Speaker's Hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Mr. Secretary <hi>Jenkins</hi> acquainteth the Houſe, that his Majeſty had been attended by the Members of his moſt Honourable Privy Council, with an Addreſs concerning Proteſtant Diſſenters. And that his Majeſty's Anſwer is, That they ſhould be diſcharged, and that without Fees, as far as might be done according to Law, and they ſhall be recommended to the Judges.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:51262:18"/>
The <hi>Parliament</hi> which then ſat, hath the repute to have been ſhort of none, who ever ſat within thoſe Walls, for Men of <hi>Honour, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Eſtates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here was plainly their <hi>Judgments</hi> declared, That theſe Acts concern not, nor ought to be extended to <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters.</hi> After which certainly that ſingle <hi>Country Juſtice,</hi> or Lawyer, who dareth to ſay <hi>they do,</hi> muſt arrogate much more to himſelf than he ought to do, conſidering how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the greateſt Lawyers of <hi>England</hi> unanimouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred in that <hi>Vote,</hi> which did not repeal thoſe Laws, nor ſtop or ſuperſede the execution of them, but only declared the ſenſe of them.</p>
               <p>If any Perſon, after all this, will affirm, <hi>they do concern them as well as others,</hi> I have nothing more to ſay againſt it, but only wiſh, That the <hi>Queſtion</hi> might be determined by my <hi>Lords</hi> the <hi>Judges,</hi> and not left to the various <hi>determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi> of puny <hi>Lawyers,</hi> and many <hi>Juſtices of the Peace,</hi> who were never bred to the <hi>Studies,</hi> nor exerciſed in the practice of our <hi>Laws.</hi> This whole Diſcourſe is but a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion from my proper Theme; for admit thoſe Statutes do concern <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> it is another Queſtion, Whether <hi>Grand-Juries, finding ſuch Indictments, be Evidence to a Petit-Jury in the Caſe?</hi> The <hi>Affirmative part</hi> of which I never look to find determined by <hi>Judges;</hi> what-ever be determined as to the other Queſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:51262:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A Pathetical Concluſion to Jurors, to conſider what they have done, to repent, and to their Ability to make ſatisfaction, avoiding the like enormous practices for the future: And to ſuch as are Commiſſioners of the Peace, not to be any Temptation to them to bring ſuch Guilt upon themſelves, their Families and Country.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHat can remain further, but that as an Orator for the Great God of Heaven and Earth, I ſhould admoniſh all my Country-men, who have been deluded by their own Luſts and Paſſions, or over-awed by any others, to make any ſuch <hi>Preſentments</hi> of things whereof they had no <hi>knowledg,</hi> or which <hi>they could not do in Truth,</hi> or to find any ſuch <hi>Indictments</hi> without any <hi>Evidence,</hi> and this after that in <hi>Judgment</hi> they had <hi>called God to Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> that they would <hi>preſent nothing but the Truth,</hi> and <hi>what came to their knowledg,</hi> and <hi>true Deliverance make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Evidence.</hi> And after they had ſealed this their Promiſory Oath, by <hi>diſclaiming any deſire of help, or Salvation, from God and his Goſpel, if they do preſent any thing but the Truth, that ſhould come to their knowledg;</hi> or <hi>find any otherwiſe than according to their Evidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That they would every one make haſte, and bring their <hi>Treſpaſs Offering to the Lord,</hi> by a ſerious confeſſion of an <hi>Iniquity,</hi> than which hardly any is capable of higher <hi>aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> and make <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to their Neighbours for the wrong they have done them by <hi>forſwearing themſelves,</hi> (in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51262:19"/>
which Caſe no Divines will ſay <hi>Repentance</hi> is true, without what <hi>Satisfaction</hi> we are able to give our Neighbours); up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Souls will lie the <hi>cries</hi> of <hi>Parents, Husbands,</hi> Wives, and Children, impriſoned, or ruined and undone, by their going expreſly contrary to their <hi>Oaths</hi> in <hi>Judgment;</hi> and let them be aſſured, there is <hi>Wrath</hi> againſt them from the Lord; and if thoſe Texts, <hi>Zech.</hi> 5. 4. and <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 5. be pieces of Holy Writ, <hi>God will be a ſwift Witneſs againſt them;</hi> and the <hi>Curſe of God will enter into their Houſes, and abide there until it hath conſumed the Timber thereof, and the Stones there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi> If therefore you believe <hi>there is a God,</hi> or that the <hi>Scriptures are the Word of God;</hi> If you believe that <hi>both your Bodies and Souls are ſubject to the Power and Juſtice of God,</hi> both <hi>in this Life, and that which is to come,</hi> ſhew it by <hi>fearing</hi> to <hi>ſwear,</hi> and not punctually doing according to what you have ſworn. There is no greater indication of <hi>Atheiſts</hi> than <hi>ſwearing falſly,</hi> or not performing punctually what they have ſworn. Nor is it poſſible that there ſhould be a more infamous Peſt of Humane Society. True Oaths in Judgment preſerve and uphold it; <hi>falſe ſwearing</hi> deſtroys it, and turneth it into an Herd of Beaſts: for it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Juſtice ſhould be ſupported, where the <hi>Religion of an Oath</hi> is loſt. Whoſoever ſweareth falſly to the prejudice of his Neighbour, whether as a <hi>Juror</hi> or a <hi>Witneſs,</hi> is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Law of God; and though his Judgment may ſleep awhile, yet it is not probable it ſhould ſleep long, when demanded of the <hi>Righteous Judg,</hi> by the <hi>importunate Cries</hi> of ſo many as are oppreſſed by it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And let it not be accounted <hi>preſumption</hi> in me, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech ſuch worthy <hi>Gentlemen</hi> as his <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath thought fit to dignify with the <hi>Commiſſion of the Peace,</hi> to conſider what they do in Cauſes of this Nature. Thoſe Noble and Worthy <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> cannot but know that it is moſt noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly <hi>contrary to the Law of England,</hi> for thoſe who are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51262:19"/>
                  <hi>Judges,</hi> in any caſe to influence <hi>Jurors,</hi> or <hi>Witneſſes;</hi> who being under <hi>Oaths,</hi> ought to be left free to the <hi>true Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance</hi> of them, and not urged either to what is <hi>certainly,</hi> or is in their opinion a <hi>violation</hi> of them. <hi>Witneſſes</hi> ought not to be <hi>inſtructed;</hi> and to be ſo <hi>inſtructed,</hi> is enough, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all juſt Laws in the World, <hi>to invalidate their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. Conſtables</hi> in their <hi>Preſentments,</hi> given in at <hi>Aſſizes</hi> and <hi>Seſſions,</hi> are <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> they are (generally) all the <hi>Evidence Grand-Jurors</hi> have, unleſs ſome <hi>Informers</hi> (which is very rare) ſwear ſuch <hi>Informations</hi> or <hi>Indictments</hi> before them: Or ſome of their own Body know the Matter of Fact to be true, which as rarely happeneth. To <hi>inſtruct</hi> them, and much more to <hi>threaten</hi> and <hi>fright</hi> them into ſuch <hi>Preſentments,</hi> is the boldeſt violation of all Laws, both of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> that is imaginable. <hi>Judges</hi> have no more to do, than to <hi>declare the Law,</hi> and to receive ſuch <hi>Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of Facts contrary to it, as Perſons upon Oath ſhall give freely, according to their Conſciences. If Perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Oaths</hi> to make Preſentments, do not make them truly, they may be <hi>legally</hi> proſecuted for their <hi>Concealments;</hi> but to force them, being upon their <hi>Oaths,</hi> to make <hi>Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> which they profeſs they cannot do in Truth, is what is neither juſtifiable to God nor Men. That <hi>Jurors</hi> are not <hi>finable</hi> by <hi>Judges</hi> for their <hi>Verdicts,</hi> hath been reſolved twice within theſe few Years; once by <hi>Parliament,</hi> in the Year 1677, in the Caſe of my <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice Keeling,</hi> who had fined a <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> for not finding an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment</hi> of <hi>Murder,</hi> for which they ſaw no Evidence. The <hi>Parliament</hi> judged, That the <hi>Preſidents and Practices of fining Juries, in, and for not giving their Verdicts,</hi> is <hi>Illegal,</hi> and the <hi>Chief Juſtice was then for it brought upon his Knees to the Bar of the Houſe of Commons.</hi> The other by the <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of the <hi>Common Pleas,</hi> in <hi>Brown Buſhel</hi>'s <hi>Caſe,</hi> largely reported by my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Vaughan;</hi> and certainly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51262:20"/>
they are no more to be over-awed and threatned, than to be fined. The Wiſe Man commandeth us, ſaying, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 10. <hi>Remove not the old Land-mark, and enter not into the Fields of the Fatherleſs.</hi> The <hi>removing of old Land-marks in Judgment, and entring into the Fields of the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> uſually follow the one the other; they are ſeldom or never removed, but in order to ſome notorious Oppreſſion: The Curſe of God therefore is againſt them that do it; <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. 17. Our Fore-fathers ſet theſe as <hi>Land-marks,</hi> for Publick <hi>Juſtice,</hi> That no Perſons in our Publick Courts of <hi>Judicature ſhould be deprived of Life, Liberty, or Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but by the Judgment of at leaſt</hi> 24. <hi>Perſons;</hi> twelve or more to enquire whether there were any probably juſt ground, ſo much as to call in Queſtion ſuch a Perſon for ſuch a Crime, for which any ſuch Puniſhment ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted; other twelve, to try the thing in iſſue, according to ſuch Evidence as they ſhould have upon Oath given of it. <hi>That neither the firſt nor ſecond of theſe Juries ſhould be awed, or threatned into their Verdict, nor fined for it, but left to their Conſciences upon their Oaths.</hi> That <hi>nothing ſhould be found againſt any but upon good and ſufficient Evidence of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and legal Witneſſes.</hi> If theſe ancient <hi>Land-marks</hi> be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, we ſhall ſoon ſee <hi>entring into the Fields of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. I ſhall conclude with another ſaying of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. 10. 8. <hi>He that diggeth a Pit, ſhall fall into it; and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo breaketh an Hedg, a Serpent ſhall bite him.</hi> Thoſe that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the juſt Order and Boundaries of Law, founded upon <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> uſually pay for their Folly; cutting up a <hi>Bridg,</hi> which at one time or other <hi>they</hi> or their <hi>Children</hi> will want for themſelves to paſs over, for the avoiding of the hands of Violence and Oppreſſion. We ſhall obſerve that the Righteous God puniſheth no Sins ſo frequently by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliation,</hi> as thoſe which are againſt <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51262:20"/>
therein he infinitely commendeth his Love to <hi>humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,</hi> for the preſervation and upholding of it, againſt the brutiſh Paſſions of thoſe who will deny their own reaſon to diſturb it; and abjure their Manhood, to prove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Creatures, meerly under the conduct of their <hi>concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible</hi> or <hi>irraſcible Appetite;</hi> from which <hi>ſottiſhneſs</hi> let every good Man deliver himſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>There is lately publiſhed a uſeful Treatiſe for this preſent Juncture, Intituled, <hi>The Caſe and Cure of Perſons Excommunicated, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the preſent Law of</hi> England. With ſome Friendly Advice to Perſons purſued in Inferior <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts</hi> by <hi>Malicious Promoters;</hi> both in order to their <hi>avoiding Excommunication,</hi> or <hi>delivering</hi> themſelves from <hi>Priſons,</hi> if impriſoned, <hi>becauſe they have ſtood Excommunicated Fourty days.</hi> With an account of their ſeveral Fees due in thoſe Courts. Sold by <hi>Richard Janeway.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
